<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-13T12:21:57-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Elijah’s Blog</title><subtitle>My name is Elijah Tabachnik, I&apos;m an aspiring Game Developer studying Computer Science at UCI. I love strategy games, hiking and of course making games.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">2135: A Sci-Fi Sketch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/03/23/2135-SciFi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2135: A Sci-Fi Sketch" /><published>2024-03-23T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-03-23T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/03/23/2135-SciFi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/03/23/2135-SciFi.html"><![CDATA[<p>Basic Outline:</p>

<p>Due to the technological creation of fusion technology, on earth, corporations in unison with governments begin terraforming a second planet in the system, Mars, then through the creation of a partial dyson sphere, with about 0.01 percent coverage of the sun through massive solar panel arrays. This as well as technological advancements allow for Weyl Wormholes, which require immense amounts of energy provided by the dyson sphere. However, there need to be two ships at both locations to allow for the creation of a wormhole so relativistic travel, about 25 percent the speed of light. This allows for the colonization of Alpha-Centauri and with the use of Weyl Wormholes instantaneous connection between the solar system and Alpha-Centauri is capable of occuring. Proxima Centauri b, a planet in Alpha-Centauri is a habitable exoplanet that is colonized. Terraforming has also begun. This and mars’ terraforming/colonization had been mostly undertaken by corporations and some governments, however, due to unrest and a lack of democratization on Earth, as well as climate change, a world government took over. During this unrest period both Mars and Centauri B proclaim independence.</p>

<p>The United Council
Outline:</p>

<p>The United Council(UC) is the main governing body of Earth, after the period of unrest known The Catastrophe, 2110 A.D, a council of the leading nations at the time was established– the remnants of the United States, China, The Russian Federation, The European Union and the Indian Empire re established control through in a federated system, the UC. The Catastrophe, also referred to as the Third World War, began due to a mixture of issues, at the forefront of these was climate change which drastically redefined the political, social and cultural realities of Earth as the center of power. Rising sea levels, increased temperatures, disease, ecosystem collapse all affected the great nations differently.</p>

<p>The United States was the least affected owing to its large reserves of natural resources, arable land and geographic diversity. The European Union which at before The Catastrophe was a loose confederation of states that did not include the United Kingdom much of Eastern Europe and the Balkans was transformed. Due to the cooling of the Gulf Stream the United Kingdom entered an ice age, with its climate resembling Iceland. The effect of the cooling of Gulf Stream affected all of Europe however, leading to an overall cooling which ultimately led to the need for central governance in the form of a strong European Union based in Madrid and Rome, the economic centers of Europe at the time. Spain, Portugal and Italy were able to survive the cooling of Northern/Eastern Europe due to their proximity to the Equator and took in massive waves of immigration, nearly a quarter of the remaining Northern/Eastern European population would end up immigration to Spain, Portugal and eventually Greece. Global Climate change would transform the European Union the most drastically outside of The Russian Federation.</p>

<p>For Russia, the Climate change was a massive boon. By the mid 2000s the Federation was in decline, after its failure to conquer Ukraine in the 2020s, Russia endured a period of unrest, economic stagnation and international weakening. However, in the latter half of the 21st century climate warming dramatically transformed. The cold harsh arctic tundras that made up the majority of the country would find themselves transfigured into the most habitable, agriculturally stable and flourishing lands in the world. Due to the mass immigration endured by the Federation during this period extreme measures were taken to transform the immigrating population into Cultural Russians. By the waning years of the 21st century, Russia produced nearly half of the world’s food products, single handedly propping up the population of the European Union and the coastal population of China. This turned Russia into a superpower, especially when coupled with the discovery of new resources caused by Siberian settlement. Ultimately this would lead to The Catastrophe, when China would invade Eastern Siberia in order to provide for its still sizable population which could barely survive on the less-habitable land in China proper.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi2.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
Russian City of Yakutsk, the regional Capital of Siberia, 2089 A.D.</p>

<p>China was affected significantly by Climate change as well. The vast river systems and wetlands that made up the country and provided for its fertility dried up due to global warming. Due to population decline, the need for fertile land was made less necessary, however eventually climate change caught up. With too large a population and not enough land to provide food, livable conditions, the majority of the population gathered around the coast and the rest immigrated to various countries, mostly Russia.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi1.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
Chinese Wasteland, 2070 A.D.</p>

<p>The Indian Empire was most negatively affected by climate change facing drought, famine, heat waves and ultimately population collapse. This period was darkest in the country’s history and led to the rise of dictators that would come to define the country and create its Empire, which pushed in all directions looking for more arable land.</p>

<p>Due to the rise of superpowers as the main forms of government, controlling more than 60% of the population in total by the time of The Catastrophe, circa 2100, neutral parts of the world suffered severely. In South America due to a mixture of political instability and climate change, famine and population collapse would lead to the establishment of local governments on a very small scale. In Africa, the Sahara would become a taker of souls, wiping out entire countries, leading to mass refugee crises. Due to climate change the Sahara would end up consuming the vast majority of Africa stopping only at the Congo. While the Island nations of the world including Japan and Polynesia, suffered greatly losing arable coastal land and some even disappearing entirely.</p>

<p>The Catastrophe:</p>

<p>The Catastrophe was the largest conflict since the Second World War. After more than one and half centuries of relative peace, Earth erupted into a massively brutal conflict that would rearrange its political, cultural and socio-economic landscape. It was in 2110, when the Chinese military entered Russian East-Siberia. This invasion was at its core one based around arable land. After the Global Crises of the late 21st century China was a husk of its former self, still wielding a relatively massive population, although nearly halved from its 2020s height. The main issues affecting the country were surrounding its lack of land, specifically the desertification of the interior of the country, which led to the coasts becoming nearly the sole population centers. This coupled with the flourishing of the neighboring Siberian Tundra led to Chinese politicians to begin plans for territorial expansion. This began initially with large military buildups, training and ramping up of arms manufacturing and the size of the military which took a backseat during the 21st century crises. Border conflicts and skirmishes began around the turn of the century and would eventually involve hundreds of thousands of troops on both sides. International mediation led by the United States through the United Nations managed to de-escalate the situation through territorial trades that often disadvantaged Russia by exchanging useless interior Chinese deserts for prime Siberian lands. However, the year 2110 heralded the worst effects of climate change, during the 2109 summer the monsoons in combination with sea flooding wreaked havoc on the coast. The Chinese government taking extreme measures were able to manage the effects, however, the decision cemented that Siberia would fall. A surprise attack was launched in the spring which destroyed the majority of the Russian Eastern Army. By winter 2110 Chinese troops entered the Siberian Capital of Yakutsk. Moscow leadership, shocked, took extreme measures, enlisting local recruits and authorizing the use of battlefield nuclear weapons. Due to the Alliance between the Russian Federation and the Indian Empire, China was flanked, however due to the ceaseless mountains in Tibet and Nepal as well as the vast deserts of the interior the Indian Army was unable to make meaningful progress. Throughout the years of the war China was slowly pushed back and eventually completely out of Siberia, however this took many years and during this period devastation ruled. While the European Union was diplomatically and economically close to China due to their manufacturing and anti-Russian stance, this war destroyed the backbone of Europe. Russian food exports made up 60% of European foodstuffs and while the Chinese attempted to keep up agriculture in Siberia during their occupation, they were unable to feed Europe. This led to years of famine and declining economic and political outcomes for the subcontinent. The entire world fell into a depression of massive proportions, in the United States this was the greatest effect of the Catastrophe. As Russian and Indian soldiers got closer and closer to Beijing the Chinese government began taking more extreme steps, expending their nuclear stockpile and using children as well as the old. The peak of this was the bombing of Moscow and Delhi. The response to this was a massive nuclear bombardment that left China in shambles. This was the final straw for the United States and the European Union which invaded China and destroyed the regime with the aid of a disgruntled and tired population. However, the Catastrophe was just beginning, the massive use of nuclear weapons against China would plunge the world into a sunless winter which destroyed crops, caused the coldest winter in the history of Civilization and crushed many of the remaining structures that had been able to withstand the climate crises of the previous century. In Europe mass famine and cold caused widespread destruction, Chinese citizens who had just lived through years of war faced similar issues. This led to the creation of the United Council, a federated government that was created to encompass all nations on Earth and deal with the Catastrophe that had engulfed the planet.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi3.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
Chinese hovercraft takes an image of victorious troops entering Yakutsk, 2110 A.D.</p>

<p>The United Council:</p>

<p>The United Council was at its core an oligarchic-authoritarian government, in so far as it was composed of 3 leaders from each of the great superpowers, except for China which was reduced to 2 due to the war and the disdain toward the nation by the Indian Empire and Russia. This meant that 11 total leaders were present. The United Council held massive executive power, and immediately at its inception began consolidation of even greater power, the first step was national de-proliferation, and the creation of a nuclear arsenal solely under the control of the Council. While the Council was authoritarian in nature the need for a federated system in which the many member and non-superpower states that had no real stake in the council had forms of self-governance. This meant that every nation had a high degree of control over internal affairs, but external affairs were handled solely by the UC. This meant the creation of a standardized space force and broad powers over taxation.</p>

<p>By 2125 the United Council had fully cemented control over Earth and established itself as the sole legitimate authority on Earth. At this point borders had little meaning on the planet, migration was largely non-regulated. However, due to many economic initiatives as well as the stability the Council brought in the wake of the Catastrophe, migration was not a damaging condition as had been in previous centuries.</p>

<p>As the need for a strong hand decreased more democratization occurred, with elections being held that encompassed every portion of the world, with the caveat of more representation being given to the previous superpowers, with a similar system in play as the late United States republic, which was the driving factor behind world governance.</p>

<p>Post Catastrophe Economy:</p>

<p>While the Catastrophe wreaked havoc on the already tenuous manufacturing, agricultural and energy situation on Earth, the post-Catastrophe planet was able to quickly reshape this reality. This was, rather morbidly, largely due to population collapse. Europe saw a 25% decline in population, from famine alone, China a 40% decrease due to famine, war and nuclear bombing. Russia a 17% decline and India a 16% decline. This facilitated a grand restructuring of Earth, with a huge population transfer towards the newly habitable areas away from the no longer habitable areas before, this was achieved through authoritarian measures the UC was able to implement. Furthermore, with the complete erasure of international trade as a reality(with the creation of a single unified Earth) manufacturing boomed. Through planetwide decrees the agricultural situation was resolved and the central planning of grids allowed for the full implementation of fusion technology. By 2125 the gross domestic product of the planet was almost double what it had been before the Catastrophe.</p>

<p>However, this economic boom had reached a plateau as the resources of the Earth were strained due to the new economic heights being achieved. And as before the Catastrophe Earth looked outside itself. But things were not as they had been before. On Mars and Centauri B nearly a decade of silence from the mother planet had reshaped the relationship between the outlanders and their own potential sovereignty.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi4.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
Post-Catastrophe Manufacturing Commune, 2123 A.D.</p>

<p>Mars
Outline:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi5.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
First Man on Mars, 2044 A.D.</p>

<p>The first man and woman set foot on Mars on the 80th anniversary of the moon landings in 2044. However much like the moon landings they went straight home and it would be another decade before man would set foot on the red planet. However, the second time humanity came it would stay. Though initially a national colony, two to be specific, one from the United States and the other China, humanity’s presence on Mars would soon be overtaken by corporations. After the discovery of significant reservoirs of precious metals and a huge variety of resources a frenzy of colonization and terraforming began. While at first lethargic and confined to underground cities, humanity dreamed of greater heights, of a green paradise reshaped in man’s image. Gaia was their key, an Artificial Intelligence supercomputer funded by the three major transnational corporations, which could handle 10^30th million calculations per second, far surpassing the total computing power of the whole of humanity(some 10^25th million calculations per second). Gaia would be the key to humanity’s aspirations, running endless simulations every second of every minute of every hour of every day for half a decade the super intelligence laid out a plan for the terraforming of Mars. Using fusion technology, which allowed for a massive increase in heating of the cold atmosphere of the planet, coupled with the injection of nitrogen, oxygen and various other atmospheric elements, allowed for a livable Mars. By 2080, thirty years after the project had begun, man first untethered from his breathing implements and inhaled the ambient air of a planet one-hundred million miles away from Earth. In the next two decades, until the Catastrophe, the pace of progress on the planet was phenomenal. The entirety of the United States was colonized over the course of nearly three centuries, Mars found itself dominated by man in merely 20 years. A generation that knew only the false sun of LED’s and the hard walls of stone would walk upon a green planet, more lush and more fertile than Earth could ever be.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi6.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
A picture taken from a skyscraper on New Washington in US controlled mars, 2102 A.D.</p>

<p>Pre-Catastrophe Mars:</p>

<p>Pre-Catastrophe Mars was defined by six major divisions. The first four were under the control of each of the great superpowers, the fifth was the disparate mining, manufacturing and other capital-based industries under the control of the transnational corporations, finally were the neutral settlers. These were made up of non-superpower countries, anarchists, independent-minded colonists and for all intents and purposes everyone else. The majority of the population of Mars lived in the cities under the control of the superpowers. The main occupation was mining, Mars being rich and abundant in precious metals, gasses, and every possible imaginable resource. The second occupation was the terraforming of the planet, which since the inception of the colonial project employed a large portion of the population. However right around the time of the Catastrophe the terraforming of the planet had been largely finished. Finally agriculture was of the utmost importance on the planet, as shipping the foodstuffs for the massive population of the planet would be nearly impossible. The population of the planet while only really away from earth for one generation was vastly different. From cultural values to social etiquette and interpersonal relationships. Due to the vast efforts of the mid-21st century before the Catastrophe nearly 15 million people were on Mars. However, during the Catastrophe and in the following decade before the great revolt of 2135 there would be some 80 million Martians. This momentous feat was only possible due to a massive shift in values and familial structures. The average Martian family was expected to produce 8 children, with economic penalties being faced by those who went under this limit, and benefits to those that went over. These children would be taken care of by Artificial Intelligence caretakers.</p>

<p>Independence:</p>

<p>The fundamental issue that would propel Mars towards independence was the Catastrophe. During this period the foodstuffs, machinery and resources needed for the upkeep of the Martian economy were halted. This led to widespread poverty, famine and collapse. During this time the various national and corporate differences that had kept Mars from considering independence and widespread cooperation fell apart. Martian citizens who had always felt kin with their fellow outlanders would come together in an unprecedented way, voting in a Martian wide government. This government, the Republic of Mars, would ensure that the planet made it through the crisis. However, when the UC had reestablished its dominance and presence the republic was not what Earth had in mind as a framework for Martian governance. This would climax in the 2120 Mars skirmish which would see the Martian Republic exiled for a year before planetwide riots would reestablish the government as an intermediary between the UC and the Martian populace. From this point on both sides, the UC and the Martian people would understand that a larger scale conflict for independence was on the horizon. In fact the only reason it had not already occurred was because of the presence of United States solar destroyers, these ships carried railgun-fired nuclear weapons which were extremely difficult to intercept, and had been built to counteract anti-nuclear systems which had been getting ever better. However, the UC would repurpose these ships towards keeping Mars in check. During this stalemate, the Martian populace would commit themselves totally towards independence, increasing the birthing of children, economic development and most importantly a cultural preparation, in which children were taught that independence was the ultimate goal. By 2030 the population of Mars was ready for independence.</p>

<p>Tensions simmered between the two worlds, fueled by conflicting interests and ideologies. Martian leaders found themselves locked in a delicate dance of diplomacy and brinkmanship, navigating a treacherous political landscape with skill and determination. Yet despite the looming shadow of Earth’s influence, the people of Mars remained steadfast in their resolve. Rallying around the banner of freedom and self-determination, they stood united in their quest to break free from the shackles of tyranny and forge their own destiny among the stars. As Mars began to further assert its independence and assert its sovereignty, tensions between the red planet and its blue counterpart reached a boiling point. The United Council, unwilling to relinquish its grip on its Martian colonies, deployed military assets to assert its authority and quell dissent.  But Mars was not to be cowed into submission. The Republic of Mars, bolstered by a burgeoning space force and a fiercely loyal populace, stood ready to defend its newfound freedom at all costs. Battles raged across the Martian surface and in the depths of space, as Earth and Mars clashed in a struggle for supremacy.  The conflict, which came to be known as the War of Martian Independence, would go down in history as one of the most epic struggles for freedom and self-determination ever waged. On one side stood the might of Earth’s military-industrial complex, with its vast resources and formidable firepower. On the other stood the indomitable spirit of the Martian people, united in their determination to carve out their own destiny among the stars.  The war exacted a heavy toll on both sides, claiming countless lives and wreaking havoc on both Earth and Mars. But in the end, it was the resilience and determination of the Martian people that proved decisive. After years of grueling conflict and untold sacrifice, Mars emerged victorious, its independence secured and its sovereignty affirmed.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/SciFi6.jpg" height="768" width="768" /> 
Independence Day parade on Mars, 2130 A.D.</p>

<p>A New Chapter in Martian History:</p>

<p>Following the conclusion of the War of Martian Independence, Mars stood at the dawn of a transformative era in its history. Liberated from the chains of colonial domination, the red planet embarked on a path of exploration and self-improvement, aiming to become a symbol of liberty and advancement within the solar system. The Martian Republic, now recognized as the sovereign authority of Mars, initiated a comprehensive plan to rejuvenate Martian society. Significant investments were directed towards infrastructure enhancements, educational reforms, and economic growth initiatives, setting the stage for a flourishing Martian civilization.  However, the remnants of the conflict were pervasive, and the road to recovery for Mars was strewn with hurdles. The task of reconstructing devastated urban areas, restoring damaged ecosystems, and mending the societal fabric torn by war demanded considerable time, dedication, and resources. Nonetheless, empowered by a resilient populace and inspired by the principles of freedom and democracy, Mars was ready to face these challenges head-on.  As dawn broke over the Martian landscape, illuminating a planet that was beginning to heal, the inhabitants of Mars looked forward with a sense of hope and anticipation. They recognized that the path ahead was fraught with difficulties, but they were united in their conviction that together, they could surmount any obstacle. Armed with bravery and a relentless drive, the Martians commenced a new journey, eager to pen the next chapter in the grand narrative of humanity’s pursuit of liberty, advancement, and discovery.</p>

<p>Post-Independence Mars:</p>

<p>Post-Independence Mars witnessed a remarkable transformation in its societal organization, shaped by the crucible of struggle for autonomy and self-determination. With independence achieved, the Martian populace embarked on a journey to establish a society reflective of their values, aspirations, and unique challenges.  The quest for independence left an indelible mark on the Martian psyche, instilling a deep sense of martial focus and preparedness within the population. Years of conflict with Earth’s governing body, the United Council, reinforced the importance of military readiness and defense as pillars of Martian identity.  The Martian Defense Force (MDF) emerged as the vanguard of Martian sovereignty, tasked with safeguarding the planet against external threats and ensuring the security of its borders. Comprising highly trained soldiers, adept strategists, and cutting-edge technology, the MDF stood as a symbol of the lessons learned during the independence war and marking the distrust of Earth.  Martial values permeated all aspects of Martian society, shaping not only military doctrine but also cultural norms and civic life. Discipline, loyalty, and courage became revered virtues, celebrated in literature, art, and communal rituals. The martial ethos cultivated a sense of unity and solidarity among Martians, forging bonds that transcended individual differences and fostered a collective identity.</p>

<p>Central to the post-independence Martian ethos were highly civic-centered values, emphasizing civic duty, communal responsibility, and participatory governance. The struggle for independence imbued Martians with a profound appreciation for civic engagement and sacrifice for the collective. The Republic of Mars adopted a decentralized governance model, empowering local communities and citizen assemblies to make decisions that directly impacted their lives. While relegating inter-communal governance to the Republic which had immense powers over the vastness of Mars that wasn’t yet population. Participatory democracy flourished, with citizens engaging in open debates, consensus-building, and direct action to address pressing issues and chart the course of their collective future. Community bonds strengthened as Martians rallied around shared civic goals and common interests. This civic pride ran deep, fueling a sense of belonging and ownership in the shaping of Martian institutions and policies.</p>

<p>While independence brought newfound freedom and autonomy, it also ushered in an era of extreme exploitation of Mars’s fragile environment. The pursuit of economic growth and technological advancement in order to keep the perceived threat of the UC at bay, led to widespread exploitation of Martian resources, with little regard for the long-term consequences.  Mining operations expanded exponentially, driven by insatiable demand for rare minerals, precious metals, and energy resources. Martian landscapes bore the scars of relentless extraction, as vast swaths of terrain were excavated and depleted to feed the voracious appetite of industrial civilization. The Martian government, eager to capitalize on its newfound independence, prioritized economic development at the expense of environmental conservation. Environmental regulations were lax, enforcement mechanisms weak, and oversight agencies understaffed and underfunded. The result was unchecked pollution, and ecological degradation, threatening the delicate balance of Mars’s biosphere. Despite mounting concerns and calls for sustainable development, the allure of economic prosperity and technological advancement prevailed, driving Martians to exploit their environment to its limits. The consequences of this shortsighted approach would reverberate for generations to come, challenging the resilience of Martian ecosystems and the viability of future settlements. In the wake of independence, Post-Independence Mars stood at a crossroads. Martians navigated the challenges of nation-building and planetary stewardship, they faced profound moral and ethical dilemmas that would shape the destiny of their society and the legacy they would leave for future generations.</p>

<p>Centauri B</p>

<p>Outline:</p>

<p>In the wake of humanity’s relentless pursuit of expansion and survival, the colonization of Alpha Centauri presented an unparalleled frontier. The spark that ignited this monumental endeavor was Earth’s mastery of fusion technology, a leap that not only reshaped the terrains of Mars but also harnessed the sun’s energy through an embryonic Dyson sphere. This technological marvel, though covering a mere 0.01 percent of the sun, revolutionized energy acquisition, paving the way for the theoretical Weyl Wormholes. These wormholes, bridges through the fabric of space, necessitated prodigious amounts of energy, supplied in abundance by the solar arrays of the Dyson sphere. The catch, however, lay in the requirement of twin ships to anchor the wormholes’ ends across vast cosmic distances. It was this innovation that stretched humanity’s reach to the stars, achieving relativistic travel at about 25 percent the speed of light and, ultimately, the colonization of Alpha Centauri.
Alpha Centauri, a system of stars closer than any other to our solar system, became the stage for humanity’s most ambitious chapter. Proxima Centauri b, an exoplanet within this system, emerged as a beacon of habitability and potential. Here, the dreams of terraforming took root once more, driven by the same corporations and government alliances that had transformed Mars. Yet, as these distant worlds began to feel the touch of human ingenuity, Earth itself was ensnared in turmoil. Climate change, societal unrest, and the thirst for democratization led to the rise of the United Council (UC), a world government formed in the aftermath of global catastrophe. Amidst this turmoil, both Mars and Centauri B declared their independence, setting the stage for a new era of interstellar sovereignty.
Terraforming:
The terraforming of Proxima Centauri b was not merely an extension of human will but a necessity. Amidst the backdrop of a recovering Earth and an independent Mars, corporations and remnants of national governments embarked on this grand project. The approach mirrored the endeavors on Mars, albeit with advancements born from lessons learned and technology refined. The Centauri Terraforming Initiative (CTI) became the vanguard of this mission, employing advanced fusion reactors to warm the planet, and releasing tailored microbes to convert its atmosphere into one breathable for humans. As the terraforming progressed, the societal fabric of Centauri B began to weave itself. The initial colonies were corporate-run, their governance reflecting the efficiency and hierarchy characteristic of their Earthly counterparts. However, as the population grew, so too did the complexity of its society. Settlements sprawled across the terraformed landscapes, each becoming a melting pot of cultures and ideologies brought from Earth and Mars. These communities, while diverse, shared a common trait, a fierce independence and a desire to shape their own destinies away from the shadows of Earth’s United Council.
Independence:
As Centauri B flourished under the guidance of the Centauri Terraforming Initiative, the seeds of independence were being sown. The initial phase of colonization, heavily influenced by corporate interests and Earth’s political ambitions, began to clash with the growing sense of identity and autonomy among the Centauri settlers. These pioneers, who had left their homes behind to venture into the unknown, started to view themselves not just as extensions of Earth’s will, but as the architects of a new civilization. The transformation of Centauri B’s landscape paralleled the transformation in the collective mindset of its inhabitants. They were no longer just survivors in a foreign land but custodians of a new world. The push for independence on Centauri B was fueled by several key factors. The distance from Earth created a natural barrier to direct governance, but more than the vast expanse of space, it was the difference in experiences and challenges that widened the gap. The colonists dealt with issues unique to their new world, from managing the fragile ecosystem of a terraformed planet to adapting human culture to this fresh context. Additionally, technological advancements, particularly in communication and resource management, fostered a sense of self-sufficiency. However, the catalyst for the formal declaration of independence was a series of legislative measures imposed by the United Council that sought to regulate the exploitation of Centauri B’s resources. These measures were seen as exploitative and dismissive of the colonists’ efforts to build a sustainable economy. The final straw came when a tax was levied on all exports to Earth, designed to benefit the UC’s coffers without considering the developmental needs of Centauri B.
The declaration was a carefully orchestrated event, designed to demonstrate not only Centauri B’s desire for sovereignty but its capability to stand as an independent entity. The Centauri Assembly, a governing body that had gradually emerged from the coalition of corporate and community leaders, drafted the declaration. It was a document that articulated their right to self-determination, drawing on the universal principles of freedom, equity, and the pursuit of happiness. The declaration was transmitted across the solar system, a symbolic act of defiance against the UC’s authority, and an invitation for diplomatic recognition from other human settlements, including Mars.
The UC’s response to Centauri B’s declaration of independence was initially one of dismissal, underestimating the resolve and capabilities of the Centauri settlers. However, as it became clear that Centauri B was united in its pursuit of independence, the UC was forced to reconsider its stance. Negotiations were fraught with tension, with the UC attempting to impose conditions that would ensure continued economic benefits from Centauri B. Yet, the settlers’ unwavering stance, coupled with diplomatic support from Mars and other sympathetic entities, gradually shifted the balance of power.
The Road to Sovereignty:
The road to sovereignty for Centauri B was marked by diplomatic maneuvers, economic restructuring, and the establishment of a defensive posture to deter any attempts at military coercion. The Centauri Defense Coalition, formed from the planet’s security forces and augmented by advanced defense systems developed in secret, stood ready to defend their independence. Simultaneously, the Centauri Assembly worked to build alliances, specifically with the nascent Martian Republic to oppose the power of the UC.
Culture:</p>

<p>The culture of Centauri B, shaped under the twin stars of Alpha Centauri, is a testament to the pioneering spirit of its settlers. Having ventured across the cosmos to start anew, these individuals brought with them a deep-seated desire for autonomy and a skepticism towards centralized authority. This sentiment was not born out of anarchy but a profound belief in the capabilities of communities to govern themselves and innovate without the heavy hand of a distant government dictating their every move. At the core of Centauri B’s society lies a commitment to decentralized governance. This ethos is rooted in the settlers’ initial experiences of corporate and Earth-centric control, which they found to be stifling and out of touch with the realities of living on a new planet. The desire for autonomy led to the development of a societal structure that emphasized local governance, community decision-making, and a flexible approach to law and order that could adapt to the diverse needs of Centauri B’s inhabitants.</p>

<p>Instead of a central government, Centauri B is dotted with numerous community councils, each responsible for the governance of their local area. These councils operate on principles of participatory democracy, where every member of the community has a voice and a vote in the decisions that affect their daily lives. From the allocation of resources to the implementation of terraforming projects, the community councils ensure that the needs and wishes of the local population are at the forefront of every decision. The anti-government sentiment of Centauri B’s populace does not equate to a rejection of organization or progress. On the contrary, the planet has become a hotbed of innovation, driven by the principle that the best ideas flourish in an environment of freedom and collaboration. Without the red tape and bureaucratic hurdles common to centralized systems, technological and social innovations rapidly evolve and spread across the planet.  In this decentralized environment, research collectives and innovation hubs have emerged as the primary drivers of technological advancement. These collectives operate as open-source communities, sharing their discoveries and inventions freely. This culture of open collaboration has led to breakthroughs in sustainable living, terraforming technology, and space exploration, solidifying Centauri B’s reputation as a leader in scientific innovation. The cultural landscape of Centauri B is as diverse as its governance structure. The planet hosts a myriad of festivals and artistic gatherings that celebrate the rich tapestry of cultures represented on the world. These events are more than just celebrations; they are a vibrant expression of Centauri B’s decentralized ethos, where every culture, community, and individual has a place and a voice.  Artistic expression on Centauri B is characterized by its use of advanced technologies, blending traditional methods with the latest innovations to create works that challenge the boundaries of what is possible. From holographic installations that interact with viewers to terraformed landscapes sculpted into living art, the creativity of Centauri B’s inhabitants knows no bounds. While the decentralized culture of Centauri B has fostered a sense of community and innovation, it is not without its challenges. Coordination between disparate communities, especially in matters that affect the planet as a whole, can be complex. Environmental management and defense are two areas where the planet’s inhabitants have had to find novel solutions to ensure collective action without compromising their principles of decentralization.</p>

<p>Relationships Between the Three</p>

<p>Mars and The United Council:
The interstellar struggle for resources between Earth’s United Council (UC) and the Martian Republic epitomizes the broader tension that has come to define their relationship. Central to their contention is the control over the asteroid belt, a region rich in minerals and rare metals critical for the continued technological and economic expansion of both societies. This celestial no-man’s-land has become the stage for a series of skirmishes that underscore the fragile peace hanging by a thread in the solar system. The asteroid belt, with its seemingly endless wealth, is viewed by the UC as essential to maintaining its dominance over Earth and its territories, while Mars sees it as vital for its autonomy and survival, fuelling an intense rivalry that manifests in both diplomatic channels and covert operations.
This competition has inevitably led to an arms race, with both Earth and Mars channeling significant portions of their economies into military technology. The Martian and UC fleets have been in a constant state of evolution, with each side attempting to outdo the other in firepower, speed, and stealth capabilities. The development of destroyers equipped with advanced propulsion systems, capable of maneuvering through the asteroid belt’s treacherous terrain, and missiles designed specifically to penetrate the other’s defenses, has become a priority. This technological tug-of-war extends to cyber warfare and intelligence, where both parties seek to undermine each other’s strategic advantages through espionage and counter-espionage activities. The arms race, consuming vast resources, stands as a testament to the deep-seated rivalry and mutual distrust that characterizes the UC-Martian relations, casting a long shadow over the prospects for a peaceful resolution.
On the front lines of this ongoing conflict are the Martian Marines, an elite force trained to operate in a variety of environments, including Earth’s 1g gravity, which presents unique challenges for those accustomed to the lower gravity of Mars. This rigorous training program, which includes simulations of asteroid terrain and zero-gravity combat, prepares them for potential engagements in the asteroid belt and beyond. The adaptation to Earth’s gravity is not just a physical challenge but a psychological one, demanding a level of resilience and determination that has become the hallmark of Martian military personnel. The existence of such a well-prepared force is a clear indication of Mars’s commitment to defending its interests in the asteroid belt, highlighting the lengths to which both sides are willing to go in this interplanetary standoff. This perpetual state of preparedness for conflict, while underscoring the tensions between Earth and Mars, also speaks to the broader theme of survival and sovereignty in the harsh expanse of space.</p>

<p>Mars and Centauri B:</p>

<p>The relationship between Mars and Centauri B is a complex tapestry woven with threads of alliance, competition, and shared opposition to Earth’s United Council. Ostensibly, Mars and Centauri B stand together in a strategic alliance, born out of necessity in the face of Earth’s dominating presence in the solar system. This partnership is underscored by mutual defense pacts and agreements aimed at ensuring a balance of power that can counteract the influence and military might of the UC. Both Mars and Centauri B, having declared their independence from Earth, view their cooperation as essential to maintaining their sovereignty and protecting their interests against a common adversary.
Despite their alliance, tensions simmer beneath the surface, particularly in matters of trade and the establishment of Centauri colonies that border Martian territory. These colonies, often set up in strategically valuable locations within the solar system, have led to disputes over resource rights, trade routes, and economic influence. Mars, with its well-established presence and infrastructure, views these new Centauri settlements with suspicion, concerned that they may encroach upon Martian economic zones or serve as military outposts that could threaten Mars’s security. Trade disputes have also emerged, with both sides vying for advantageous positions in the exchange of goods, technology, and information. These tensions, though contained, hint at the fragile nature of the Martian-Centauri alliance, suggesting that their partnership is as much a marriage of convenience as it is a bond of shared ideals.
Yet, despite these underlying frictions, Mars and Centauri B remain united in their stance against Earth. The threat posed by the UC, with its vast resources and military capabilities, necessitates a united front from both Mars and Centauri B. This common adversary has encouraged both parties to overlook their differences and work together on joint military exercises, research and development projects, and diplomatic initiatives aimed at strengthening their position in the solar system. The shared history of striving for independence from Earth’s control serves as a powerful reminder of their mutual interests and the potential consequences of division. In this grand chess game of interplanetary politics, Mars and Centauri B recognize that their survival and prosperity hinge not only on their ability to stand against Earth but also on their capacity to navigate the complexities of their alliance, balancing competition with cooperation in the face of a common foe.</p>

<p>Centauri B and The United Council:</p>

<p>The dynamics between Centauri B and the United Council are characterized by a paradoxical blend of enmity and interdependence, showcasing the multifaceted nature of interstellar relations. On the surface, Centauri B and the UC are clear adversaries, with a history of political and ideological conflict stemming from Centauri B’s declaration of independence and its subsequent efforts to establish itself as a sovereign power outside of Earth’s dominion. This adversarial relationship is further compounded by Centauri B’s alliance with Mars, a move that positions it directly against the UC’s interests. The narrative of rebellion against Earth’s control resonates strongly on Centauri B, fueling a sense of unity and purpose in its opposition to the UC.
Despite the overt hostility, the economic realities of the galaxy dictate a more nuanced interaction between these two powers. Earth, with its vast population and advanced industrial base, remains a crucial market for Centauri B’s exports. The planet’s unique position in the Alpha Centauri system grants it access to resources and technological innovations that are highly sought after on Earth, from rare minerals to advanced terraforming technologies and biotech developments. This economic interplay creates a complex web of dependency, where Centauri B benefits from the lucrative trade with Earth, even as it seeks to assert its independence and challenge the UC’s political hegemony. These economic links serve as a pragmatic bridge between the two, necessitating a degree of cooperation and diplomatic engagement despite their overarching rivalry.
The military dimension of the Centauri B-UC relationship is markedly different from the direct confrontations seen between Mars and Earth. Centauri B’s distance from the solar system presents both a strategic buffer and a limitation on the feasibility of military engagement. While the UC possesses a formidable spacefaring fleet capable of projecting power across the solar system, the logistical and tactical challenges of mounting operations across interstellar distances to Centauri B temper the immediate military threat. Consequently, Centauri B has focused its defensive strategies on securing its space and developing advanced technologies to deter any potential aggression, rather than engaging in an arms race comparable to that between Mars and the UC. This relative military détente, however, does not diminish the underlying tensions but rather encapsulates the cold war-like state of affairs, where economic leverage and technological superiority play a more significant role than outright military confrontation.
In this complex dance of rivalry and interdependence, Centauri B and the United Council navigate a relationship that is as much defined by their economic entanglements as it is by their political opposition. The delicate balance of asserting sovereignty while engaging in mutually beneficial trade exemplifies the nuanced realities of interstellar diplomacy, where economic interests often temper ideological divides, and the vastness of space introduces unique strategic considerations that shape the nature of conflict and cooperation.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="NPC," /><category term="Games," /><category term="Game" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Basic Outline:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Procedural Terrain and Foliage Generation in Unity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/01/20/Terrain-Generation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procedural Terrain and Foliage Generation in Unity" /><published>2024-01-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/01/20/Terrain-Generation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/01/20/Terrain-Generation.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I’ve been exploring the use of terrain generation for strategy game implementations. Specifically I’ve worked off of tutorials online about terrain generation to create a procedural terrain+foliage generator using perlin noise. You can find the project <a href="https://github.com/Elijahtab/Real-Time-Strategy-Demo">here</a>. The basic setup is to create a noise map using perlin noise and then convert it into whatever you need from there, so a height map and a texture map. For this first part I used parts of Sebastian Lague’s tutorial on the subject <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wbpMiKiSKm8&amp;list=PLFt_AvWsXl0eBW2EiBtl_sxmDtSgZBxB3">linked here</a>. And from there I added an additional noise map for the tree chunks, so that the trees weren’t random but followed a forest-like configuration.The code itself doesn’t really make too much sense out of context so I’ll explain the important part and if you’re curious to explore more you can find the ‘ObjectGenerator’ script that does most of the heavy lifting.</p>

<p>This is the most important part of the script: what it does is take in another noise map that was created and superimposes it on top of the height requirements of the original noisemap(which basically delineates where the water, grass and mountains start/end). So the superimposed noise map creates chunks of forest which can be manipulated by the treeChunkSize variable.</p>

<p>You can see the chunks are variable and can be completely randomized, like the rest of the generation.
<img src="/assets/Terrain1.png" height="390" width="956" /> 
You can make them larger
<img src="/assets/Terrain2.png" height="390" width="956" /> 
And you can even increase the density of the trees, with up to 15,000 trees before you start noticing lag, at least on my computer. I was able to achieve this by combining Unity’s built-in tree generation software with the LOD to create a fairly seamless transition. 
<img src="/assets/Terrain3.png" height="390" width="956" /> 
<img src="/assets/Terrain4.png" height="390" width="956" /> 
There’s also grass, although it is not based around chunks because grass is kind of everywhere, foliage is less chunkable, let’s put it that way.
<img src="/assets/Terrain5.png" height="390" width="956" /></p>

<p>Overall working on this has been super fun and I want explore making nature in virtual worlds more.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="NPC," /><category term="Games," /><category term="Game" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lately I’ve been exploring the use of terrain generation for strategy game implementations. Specifically I’ve worked off of tutorials online about terrain generation to create a procedural terrain+foliage generator using perlin noise. You can find the project here. The basic setup is to create a noise map using perlin noise and then convert it into whatever you need from there, so a height map and a texture map. For this first part I used parts of Sebastian Lague’s tutorial on the subject linked here. And from there I added an additional noise map for the tree chunks, so that the trees weren’t random but followed a forest-like configuration.The code itself doesn’t really make too much sense out of context so I’ll explain the important part and if you’re curious to explore more you can find the ‘ObjectGenerator’ script that does most of the heavy lifting.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recreating Historical Personalities with AI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/01/10/AI-Historical-Avatar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recreating Historical Personalities with AI" /><published>2024-01-10T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/01/10/AI-Historical-Avatar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2024/01/10/AI-Historical-Avatar.html"><![CDATA[<p>Reviving History: The Integration of AI in Recreating Iconic Personalities</p>

<p>The world is surely going to be changed by Artificial Intelligence, that’s clear to anyone in or outside of the computer related fields. As with any technology it’s going to get better and better but even what we have is quite amazing. I think at this stage like the .com era there’s going to be a rush to combine various AI-fueled technologies in order to create new products and synthesize what’s quickly advancing in LLM’s, and really anything related to AI. And that’s something that I have long been wanting to get into. Specifically the fusion of various forms of Artificial Intelligences and tools surrounding them to create something related to history, my favorite non-tech academic field. I was given the opportunity to work with some of my peers this quarter on just such a project. Our goal was to produce a very rough draft of what a talking, emoting, intelligent character could look like through a historic lens. We chose to focus on JFK due to the reservoir of audio and video images of him as well as his unique style of dictation; additionally, this wealth of digital information is coupled with the fact that he is very much a historic character in our shared imagination, at least in the United States, which makes him a good starting point. You can check out our demo <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zJehpogrUMb-EsLDKMKmc5iFWNlGiftH/view?usp=sharing">here</a>, note that there is no speech recognition in this demonstration there are preloaded questions. You can also find our pitch <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1t2uB2HAs40cONk249_zMvTMVLZGMU1tx/view?usp=sharing">right here</a>.</p>

<p>Now to get into the more technical aspects, around how I actually made the demo and the way that it is surrounded by AI:</p>

<ol>
  <li>OpenAI Integration for Personality Emulation:</li>
</ol>

<p>The centerpiece of the project was the integration of an OpenAI assistant, tailored to reflect JFK’s intellectual and speech patterns. To achieve this, we immersed the AI in a wealth of JFK’s writings, speeches, and public records. The AI, trained on this extensive dataset, was able to generate responses that were in JFK’s style of speech but also in our opinion represented roughly his ideological and political views, obviously with heavy caveats.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Speech Synthesis and Visual Representation:</li>
</ol>

<p>ElevenLabs’ speech synthesis technology played a pivotal role in this project. It analyzed JFK’s speech patterns to create a realistic vocal model. This model could articulate any given text in JFK’s distinctive voice, adding a layer of authenticity to the AI. Complementing the voice, I created a digital video portrait of JFK. This was meant to provide a responsive face that could articulate and express in sync with the AI’s responses, creating a relatively lifelike avatar of JFK.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Speech Recognition and AI Interaction:</li>
</ol>

<p>While this step remains theoretical it is a necessary precondition to creating a real interactable historical avatar and any future project would entail the creation of such a system.</p>

<p>Challenges and Innovations:</p>

<p>One of the significant challenges was ensuring the AI’s responses remained true to JFK’s character and historical context. At this point in AI development I think getting to a perfect or even near perfect level is hard, especially because there’s a lot of information about any historical figure that we simply don’t know. Then there’s the fact that even OpenAI isn’t perfect itself, there’s hallucinations and just blatantly false information, but you can get a solid amount of accuracy and believability. I implemented this through the use of texts, so autobiographies, historical documents, magazines and books about the period of JFK’s presidency and the man himself. I put these into the OpenAI assistants API and had the model adhere as strictly as possible to these documents when generating responses.</p>

<p>Another challenge was Integrating different AI technologies to work harmoniously. The project demands a seamless fusion of speech recognition, AI processing, voice synthesis, and video animation. I started the process but it would definitely take much more work to get a workable prototype.</p>

<p>Impact on Education and Historical Engagement:</p>

<p>AI opens new avenues in educational methodologies and historical engagement. It presents an innovative way to interact with history, transforming the learning experience from passive absorption to active engagement. That’s really what this project was about. Trying to get Students and history enthusiasts to be able to have a simulated conversation with JFK, a conversation that could help engagement and feeling like this is something that really happened. This is of course why I’m so interested in this project. I think that history can be very academic and cold, which is good in some ways but in others it’s limiting. History is our collective past and it defines the way we live our lives and it’s super relevant and anything that can make it more accessible and real is beautiful I think. While I’m sure I haven’t achieved that here it’s a start and I hope that I can explore this further in the future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="NPC," /><category term="Games," /><category term="Game" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reviving History: The Integration of AI in Recreating Iconic Personalities]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crafting Game Maps with Stable Diffusion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/10/26/Control-Net-Tower-Defensey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crafting Game Maps with Stable Diffusion" /><published>2023-10-26T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-26T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/10/26/Control-Net-Tower-Defensey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/10/26/Control-Net-Tower-Defensey.html"><![CDATA[<p>Artificial Intelligence will revolutionize the world around us. But it will not only do so for consumers, creators will be affected just as much if not more. Generative AI is making things that would have required hours of the work of professionals before. In my newest dive into this world, I used Stable Diffusion to do the heavy lifting for the art in my Tower Defense game. Using stable Diffusions control net extension, I was able to turn this:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/stablDiffBackground1.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>Into this:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/stableDiff11.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>Creating immersive and captivating maps for a tower defense game is a complex task that demands innovation and sophistication. In the realm of game development, there is a powerful yet relatively lesser-known tool at our disposal - Stable Diffusion. This cutting-edge technology not only empowers game designers to craft intricate and dynamic landscapes but also introduces an unprecedented level of stability and coherence to the map generation process. In this blog post, we will delve into the fascinating world of using Stable Diffusion for map design in tower defense games, exploring its limitless potential, and offering insights into how it can elevate the gaming experience to new heights. Whether you’re a seasoned game developer seeking to revamp your projects or a budding enthusiast with a passion for creating engaging game environments, this exploration of Stable Diffusion’s role in tower defense map design is bound to inspire and inform your creative journey.</p>

<p>To get started you need Stable Diffusion, I used Albert Bozeman’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nBpD-RbglPw&amp;t">video</a> on the subject to get started. He also has one on how to set up <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dLM2Gz7GR44&amp;t">control net</a>.</p>

<p>After getting all of this set up, I decided to check out my general idea. Which was to create a basic outline for which Stable Diffusion could fill in the gaps. To give some background info, there are three control-net models that I used, Scribble, Depth and Canny, with Canny being the base model that is most associated with control-net. All have the same basic idea. You input a base image and a prompt to describe what you want to happen to that image and the control-net generates something for you.</p>

<p>First I tried doing scribble mode which was suggested on some message boards and articles as a better alternative to Canny as it allowed for more fuzziness around the edges, literally and figuratively, giving the AI more leeway as well as providing a less rigid image from which to work with. However, the result was not always perfect. I definitely had to play with the prompt a bit, different types of prompts(industrial, desert, castle) had different needs, so I had to customize the prompts a bit adding different levels of ‘top down view’ or whatever that specific prompt needed. However, what I found was that using different models of control-net could yield various results that the user was looking for. So using scribble gave you more of a fluid image, while canny gave you a very rigid non-unique look, finally depth worked better sometimes than others, but definitely gave interesting backgrounds with obviously more depth.</p>

<p>Image I got using Scribble:
<img src="/assets/scribble1.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>Image I got using Canny:
<img src="/assets/canny1.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>Image I got using Depth:
<img src="/assets/depth1.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>I found that I had no favorite model as other bloggers mentioned, for me scribble, depth and canny all provided good results at different points and could be used to attain similar yet distinct backgrounds. Although scribble was by far the least dependable, having small defects and a lack of straight paths. After doing some exploring I managed to find the image that control-net uses as a base and that told me everything I needed to know about why scribble was so inaccurate:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/stablDiffBackground5.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>However, after some experimenting I realized that the power of the scribble was that it was designed to create images from meandering lines such as the one shown below:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/StableDiffBackground4.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p>Which gave me this result, which I thought was pretty cool and I ended up using it in the game itself:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/scribble2.png" height="540" width="960" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/InGameScribble.png" height="536" width="960" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="NPC," /><category term="Games," /><category term="Game" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence will revolutionize the world around us. But it will not only do so for consumers, creators will be affected just as much if not more. Generative AI is making things that would have required hours of the work of professionals before. In my newest dive into this world, I used Stable Diffusion to do the heavy lifting for the art in my Tower Defense game. Using stable Diffusions control net extension, I was able to turn this:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-Powered NPCs: Shaping the Future of Gaming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/27/Injecting-AI-Into-Games.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-Powered NPCs: Shaping the Future of Gaming" /><published>2023-09-27T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-27T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/27/Injecting-AI-Into-Games</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/27/Injecting-AI-Into-Games.html"><![CDATA[<p>The world of gaming has always been a breeding ground for innovation, and one of the most exciting frontiers in game development is the integration of artificial intelligence (AI) to create more immersive and dynamic experiences. In this blog, I’ll take you on a journey through the creation of a platformer game set in space, where the non-player characters (NPCs) are powered by OpenAI. This project not only serves as a captivating demo but also provides valuable insights into harnessing AI in gaming. So, let’s embark on this cosmic adventure!</p>

<p>Before we get started, the game I have been working on and is the subject of this article can be found <a href="https://github.com/Elijahtab/Parallaxer">here</a>. If you want to make it work on your machine, you will need to add your own OpenAI key. This can be achieved by typing in, “Edit Environmental Variables” in your windows search bar and then, after reaching the variable menu, clicking new, the title should be “OPENAI_API_KEY” and the value your API key. I discuss this in greater detail in my previous <a href="https://elijahtab.github.io/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/19/Revolutionizing-NPC's-AI.html">article</a> on the topic. Also as mentioned there-in, artificial intelligence has the potential to burst into every facet of Video Game design, NPC interactions, logic engines, storytelling etc. For this article my goal was to showcase my further explorations with this concept. This article will serve as both a showcase of the possibilities, my work and as a rough guide for getting a jumpstart in the subject. The first step for this process was setting up a unity game that had the potential to be brought to life with AI:</p>

<p>Setting Up Unity:
Begin by creating a new Unity project and setting up the necessary assets like character models, level designs, and textures. You can use ChatGPT to help with the basics, of coding and putting together the games assets. I already had the base husk of a game I had been working on at the ready, a platformer that utilized the parallax effect to create the illusion of a never star-filled space. “Starlight Parallax” used another mechanic, a dual world setup where-in there were to sets of platforms that the player could only access one at a time. Using this base I decided to add in the AI part.</p>

<p>Create a way to Acess LLMs through Unity:
I used <a href="https://github.com/OkGoDoIt/OpenAI-API-dotnet">GoDoIt’s</a> wrapper and the instructions present in his repository to help me get started.</p>

<p>Creating NPCs:
Design and model the NPCs, making them visually distinct and suited to their respective roles in the game–I used free assets available on the Unity store as this was more of a demo than a fully fledged game.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/platformer2.png" height="150" width="109" /></p>

<p>Then create animations for idle. This is something that youtube can help you with, Brackey’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hkaysu1Z-N8">video</a> on the subject is a good starting point. After that you are ready to create the actual process for sending and receiving messages with OpenAI. I personally used an inputfield for sending messages to OpenAI, a textbox with a background for recieving, as well as a button to catalyze the process.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/platformer1.png" height="411" width="472" /></p>

<p>Dialogue System:</p>

<p>Develop a dialogue system that allows the NPCs to respond to player input using natural language. Utilize OpenAI’s language generation capabilities to make the interactions feel more dynamic and engaging.</p>

<p>Behavior Patterns:
Define the NPCs’ behavior patterns. For example, some might provide crucial information about the level, while others could offer side quests or challenges. Implement decision-making logic using AI to determine NPC responses. As an example, the first character the player meets is Ralph, who’s basic purpose is to let the player know that in order to access the mechanic that switches world’s they have to press space. In order to achieve this I had to play with various prompts finally settling on</p>
<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"> <span class="n">prompt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"You are Ralph talking to the main character. Your goal is to help him understand in a subtle way that the world switches between two modes that help him do the parkour necessary to complete the levels. The player has to press space to engage this mode. Keep your responses relatively short while conveying the necessary information."</span><span class="p">;</span></code></pre></figure>
<p>.</p>

<p>This prompt led to successful interactions that let the player know what they should do next:
<img src="/assets/platformer3.png" height="520" width="769" /></p>

<p>And another one, just to prove I don’t have a secret script feeding responses:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/platformer4.png" height="512" width="724" /></p>

<p>After tweaking Ralph’s prompt and AI settings, I decided to add another character that could provide a more interesting lens into the world the player inhabits. I decided to focus on a more melancholic disposition. Sally’s prompt</p>
<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"> <span class="n">prompt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"You are Ralph talking to the main character. Your goal is to help him understand in a subtle way that the world switches between two modes that help him do the parkour necessary to complete the levels. The player has to press space to engage this mode. Keep your responses relatively short while conveying the necessary information."</span><span class="p">;</span></code></pre></figure>
<p>led to more fun responses…</p>

<p><img src="/assets/platformer5.png" height="498" width="538" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/platformer6.png" height="515" width="639" /></p>

<p>In this exploration of AI-powered NPCs in our space platformer, we’ve ventured into the exciting frontier where gaming and artificial intelligence converge. This project has illuminated the immense potential for AI to transform the gaming landscape. As we’ve witnessed, AI can bring NPCs to life in ways previously unimaginable. These characters aren’t just static entities; they’re storytellers, guides, and companions. They adapt, learn, and engage players in dynamic conversations, blurring the line between scripted content and player agency.What’s truly fascinating is the glimpse this project offers into the future of gaming. As AI technology continues to advance, we can expect even more sophisticated and realistic NPC interactions. Games will become living, breathing worlds where AI-driven characters play pivotal roles in shaping narratives and adapting to player choices.</p>

<p>Imagine a gaming experience where every playthrough is unique, where NPCs remember your decisions, and where the story unfolds in response to your actions. This is the promise of AI in gaming—a future where immersion, storytelling, and player engagement reach unprecedented heights.In conclusion, our space platformer serves as a testament to the transformative power of AI in gaming. It’s a journey that hints at the limitless possibilities awaiting both developers and players. As we look ahead, the fusion of AI and gaming promises to redefine how we experience and interact with virtual worlds, and we can’t wait to see where this cosmic adventure takes us next. The future of gaming is poised to be nothing short of extraordinary.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="NPC," /><category term="Games," /><category term="Game" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The world of gaming has always been a breeding ground for innovation, and one of the most exciting frontiers in game development is the integration of artificial intelligence (AI) to create more immersive and dynamic experiences. In this blog, I’ll take you on a journey through the creation of a platformer game set in space, where the non-player characters (NPCs) are powered by OpenAI. This project not only serves as a captivating demo but also provides valuable insights into harnessing AI in gaming. So, let’s embark on this cosmic adventure!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revolutionizing NPC Interactions: The AI Frontier in Gaming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/19/Revolutionizing-NPC's-AI.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revolutionizing NPC Interactions: The AI Frontier in Gaming" /><published>2023-09-19T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-19T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/19/Revolutionizing-NPC&apos;s-AI</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ai,/npc,/games,/game/design/2023/09/19/Revolutionizing-NPC&apos;s-AI.html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wanted to have a real conversation with a non-playable character, to truly feel a part of the world you experience through your computer screen. That isn’t far away, with the renaissance of AI we are currently living in, it’s only a matter of time before the likes of Rockstar and Ubisoft implement modern Language Model Models(LLMs) into their NPC structures. Instead of small prebuilt interactions with random passersby in Red Dead Redemption or Grand Theft Auto, the player could have hundreds or thousands of unique individualized interactions in a game world. Instead of being limited to the couple dozen base one liners the designers thought up, prompts describing the basics of an individual will be used to create limitless distinct conversations that will never happen again. Imagine riding around, finding a woman: Sophia, and exploring her lens on the game world you are inhabiting, her struggles with the industrialization and the cowboys turned bandits that you represent. That conversation can be as real as anything but a true human interaction. This would of course tamper with the pre-existing modes of storytelling in the video game industry, which revolves largely around pre-scripted events and dialogue. The designer who manages to create true interesting storylines based around AI would create something truly groundbreaking.</p>

<p>But forget about storytelling, what about giving AI agency. Meta has already shown that AI can have the <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/ai-learns-art-diplomacy-game">faculty</a> to combine communication with strategic planning. Diplomacy, a strategically simplistic game, becomes highly complex when human interaction is added. Players can talk to, banter, work together and betray each other. Meta has managed to combine objective strategic planning and subjective interaction, in an AI that outperforms the vast majority of human players.</p>

<p>This is fascinating for many reasons, but to a strategy nerd, Meta’s AI opens a world of possibilities. What happens when beloved Strategy games can be played single player with truly self-determined opponents that communicate and make decisions based on your input? A game where your advisors can dissect your strategy and that of your opponent and give you advice based on in-game happenings. But even more interesting is that these intelligences can be added in historical context. Many strategy games attempt to immerse the player in a historical period. The player could have AI imitating historical figures interacting with, advising and opposing the player. You could be interacting with Suleiman the Magnificent outside the gates of Vienna, or with Napoleon as he marches into Moscow. That’s where my interest lies, can we make characters that attempt the emulation of historical figures. Some strategy games could implement this with a mod, Civilization V’s advisors, for example, could easily be turned into historical figures. Napoleon as a military advisor, Keynes as an economic advisor, Oppenheimer helping gleam which research is most important and Bismarck counseling your foreign diplomacy.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/civ1.png" height="384" width="512" /></p>

<p>I wanted to explore this realm of Artificial Intelligence myself, with the eventual goal being fully integrating an LLM into a game. The first part of this process was to create an account with OpenAI and set up per-token billing.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/openAI1.png" height="134" width="512" /></p>

<p>You’re provided with an API key which gives you access to the API itself and is billed based on usage. This is actually an issue for creating marketable games with the API as your key both needs to be hidden, so as not to be the victim of theft, but also accessible for each user. However, I didn’t have to worry about that for this test run so I just used an environmental variable stored on my personal computer. This can be achieved by typing in, “Edit Environmental Variables” in your windows search bar and then, after reaching the variable menu, clicking new, the title should be “OPENAI_API_KEY” and the value your API key.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="n">api</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">OpenAIAPI</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">Environment</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">GetEnvironmentVariable</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"OPENAI_API_KEY"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">EnvironmentVariableTarget</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">User</span><span class="p">));</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Then I had to find an API wrapper that would do the heavy lifting of actually connecting OpenAI’s API to Unity in a usable way, I used OkGoDoIt’s repository to get a start.  I Imported the API and figured out how to actually communicate with OpenAI, a relatively easy process that at its base level requires you to submit a message and receive one back.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="n">messages</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">List</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="no">ChatMessage</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">ChatMessage</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">ChatMessageRole</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">System</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">""</span><span class="p">)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The Input</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="n">var</span> <span class="n">chatResult</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">await</span> <span class="n">api</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Chat</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">CreateChatCompletionAsync</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">ChatRequest</span><span class="p">()</span>
        <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="no">Model</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Model</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">ChatGPTTurbo</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="no">Temperature</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">.</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="no">MaxTokens</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">300</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="no">Messages</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">messages</span>
        <span class="p">});</span>


        <span class="no">ChatMessage</span> <span class="n">responseMessage</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">ChatMessage</span><span class="p">();</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The Output</p>

<p>You can find the full code in my <a href="https://github.com/Elijahtab/OpenAI-API-With-Caesar">Github Repository</a>. After finishing up the technical aspects I went about my task: emulating Julius Caesar in conversation. I did this by adding in context to tha AI, or the basis for which the AI should construct its responses. My first attempt to achieve this was to add excerpts from Julius Caesar’s writings, however I quickly discovered an issue; OpenAI has a context limit of 4096 bytes, or about a paragraph of text, a far cry from my goal of 200 pages of Caesar’s writings in De Bello Gallico and De Bello Civili. While in the future AI will certainly have the ability to process larger amounts of data, for now we are stuck with short and sweet. I did try doing some research and while I found some promising <a href="https://fortelabs.com/blog/how-to-summarize-books-using-chatgpt/">Ideas</a> nothing really worked for my goals. However, as an LLM ChatGPT has access to Julius Caesar’s writings, and even though it wouldn’t be as precise as creating a personality around them, I could just create context that called upon the models inherent knowledge. My first attempt was promising however, ‘Julius Caesar’ kept rambling to such a degree that the token limit was reached and the so the bot stopped mid-sentence.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/Notlong.png" height="512" width="1093" /></p>

<p>After tweaking the prompt:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"> <span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">ChatMessage</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">ChatMessageRole</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">System</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">"You are Julius Caesar, you will attempt to emulate him as best as possible using his writings in De Bello and De bello civili. You will never break character and always pretend you are Julius Caesar. Reply with relatively short but informative answers up to 6 sentences long."</span><span class="p">)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>It ended up working fairly well, as you can see in the following images.
<img src="/assets/Caesar1.png" height="512" width="1093" /> 
<img src="/assets/Ariovistus.png" height="512" width="1093" /></p>

<p>The intersection of artificial intelligence and gaming holds the promise of revolutionizing our gaming experiences in profound ways. The potential to engage in real, meaningful conversations with non-playable characters, thanks to modern LLMs, opens up new avenues for immersive storytelling and player interaction. The ability to create personalized interactions within game worlds, shaped by the unique characteristics of each AI-driven NPC, could redefine how we experience gaming narratives.</p>

<p>Beyond NPCs, LLMs can be used to power AI opponents in various game genres, including strategy games. These AI opponents can adapt to the player’s strategies, making the single-player experience more challenging and satisfying. As players hone their skills, AI opponents can also evolve, ensuring that the gaming experience remains engaging and competitive. The recent developments in AI, exemplified by Meta’s AI in diplomacy games, highlight the exciting possibilities of giving AI agency and strategic prowess. Gamers can look forward to challenging single-player experiences where AI opponents communicate, adapt, and strategize based on player input, enhancing the depth of gameplay. The integration of historical figures as AI advisors in strategy games offers a fascinating opportunity to immerse players in historical contexts, allowing them to interact with and learn from iconic figures of the past.</p>

<p>Furthermore, LLMs can assist in generating vast amounts of in-game content, from dialogues and quest narratives to item descriptions and world lore. This not only reduces the workload on game developers but also ensures that games are rich in content, offering players hours of exploration and discovery.I personally look forward to exploring this topic further and integrating Artificial Intelligence more fully into my Games.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="NPC," /><category term="Games," /><category term="Game" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Have you ever wanted to have a real conversation with a non-playable character, to truly feel a part of the world you experience through your computer screen. That isn’t far away, with the renaissance of AI we are currently living in, it’s only a matter of time before the likes of Rockstar and Ubisoft implement modern Language Model Models(LLMs) into their NPC structures. Instead of small prebuilt interactions with random passersby in Red Dead Redemption or Grand Theft Auto, the player could have hundreds or thousands of unique individualized interactions in a game world. Instead of being limited to the couple dozen base one liners the designers thought up, prompts describing the basics of an individual will be used to create limitless distinct conversations that will never happen again. Imagine riding around, finding a woman: Sophia, and exploring her lens on the game world you are inhabiting, her struggles with the industrialization and the cowboys turned bandits that you represent. That conversation can be as real as anything but a true human interaction. This would of course tamper with the pre-existing modes of storytelling in the video game industry, which revolves largely around pre-scripted events and dialogue. The designer who manages to create true interesting storylines based around AI would create something truly groundbreaking.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is AI the Future of Game Design?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/first/game/2023/03/07/AI-Games-Today.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is AI the Future of Game Design?" /><published>2023-03-07T17:44:32-08:00</published><updated>2023-03-07T17:44:32-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/first/game/2023/03/07/AI-Games-Today</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/first/game/2023/03/07/AI-Games-Today.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a quiet saturday and I’m studying for an upcoming test. As I survey the study lounge that is my home until the clock strikes eleven, I note the usual types – anxious procrastinators making up for lost time, socializers pretending to study, snackers that never seem to stop their chewing – but something feels off, a foreboding feeling saturates the room. My worries are actualized with a slight ping – a text from my girlfriend professing her excitement at the gift she’s gotten me for Valentines day. Horror engulfs me. How could I have forgotten, Valentine’s is only four days away and I have no gift at the ready.</p>

<p>While I know this sounds like the start to a poorly made sitcom filled with wacky antics, misplaced girlfriends and overdone tropes, it was actually the beginning of an interesting, and in my opinion astounding, journey. As I was mulling over the various cliche gifts I would have enough time to procure before that tuesday, a small, yet bright, lightbulb went off in my head. What if I made her a game? This is something I had wanted to do for a while, both to profess my affection and to further my skills as a Game Designer. But I had been putting it off for a while. So I started. However, as anyone with a mild inclination towards making games knows it is can be a painstaking and long process, especially if you are inexperienced and need to constantly utilize Stack Exchange and whatever else google can provide you. This however was a high-stakes mission and I had limited time at my disposal. So I turned to ChatGPT which I had used successfully for advice in everything from coding, to debugging, to ordering gameobjects. This was the true beginning of my foray into the world of Artificial Intelligence aided Game Design.</p>

<p>I had decided to make an infinite ‘flyer.’, Cupid’s Arrow as I would come to call it. First and foremost I had to make my protaganist move. Of course ChatGPT was my very first source. The majority of this code was directly quoted from the chatbot. Throughout the creation process, I had to ask a variety of questions and piece together what I learned as well as the code provided.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="kp">public</span> <span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">PlayerController</span> <span class="p">:</span> <span class="no">MonoBehaviour</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="n">float</span> <span class="n">moveSpeed</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="kp">private</span> <span class="no">Rigidbody2D</span> <span class="n">rb</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kp">private</span> <span class="n">float</span> <span class="n">minX</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">maxX</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">minY</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">maxY</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="n">int</span> <span class="n">health</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="no">GameObject</span> <span class="n">bulletPrefab</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="n">float</span> <span class="n">bulletSpeed</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">10</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">[</span><span class="no">SerializeField</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="n">float</span> <span class="n">bulletTimer</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="no">BulletBar</span> <span class="n">bulletBar</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="no">HealthBar</span> <span class="n">healthBar</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="no">PauseScript</span> <span class="n">pauseScript</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kp">public</span> <span class="no">GameObject</span> <span class="n">gameOverPrefab</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="kp">private</span> <span class="n">void</span> <span class="no">Start</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="n">rb</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">GetComponent</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="no">Rigidbody2D</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">();</span>
        <span class="no">Camera</span> <span class="n">mainCamera</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Camera</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="no">Vector2</span> <span class="n">screenBounds</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">mainCamera</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">ScreenToWorldPoint</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">Vector3</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">Screen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">width</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">Screen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">height</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">mainCamera</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">position</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">z</span><span class="p">));</span>
        <span class="n">minX</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">screenBounds</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">x</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">localScale</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">x</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">maxX</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">screenBounds</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">x</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">localScale</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">x</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">minY</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">screenBounds</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">y</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">localScale</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">y</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">maxY</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">screenBounds</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">y</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">localScale</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">y</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">;</span>

        <span class="n">pauseScript</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">GameObject</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Find</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"GameController"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">GetComponent</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="no">PauseScript</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">();</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="kp">private</span> <span class="n">void</span> <span class="no">Update</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="n">float</span> <span class="n">horizontal</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Input</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">GetAxis</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"Horizontal"</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="n">float</span> <span class="n">vertical</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Input</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">GetAxis</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"Vertical"</span><span class="p">);</span>

        <span class="no">Vector2</span> <span class="n">movement</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new</span> <span class="no">Vector2</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">horizontal</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">vertical</span><span class="p">);</span>

        <span class="sr">//</span> <span class="no">Clamp</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">position</span> <span class="n">to</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">screen</span> <span class="n">bounds</span>
        <span class="no">Vector3</span> <span class="n">newPosition</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">position</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="no">Vector3</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="n">movement</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">moveSpeed</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="no">Time</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">deltaTime</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">newPosition</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Mathf</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Clamp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">newPosition</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">minX</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">maxX</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="n">newPosition</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">y</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Mathf</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Clamp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">newPosition</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">y</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">minY</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">maxY</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">position</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">newPosition</span><span class="p">;</span>

        <span class="n">rb</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">velocity</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Vector2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">zero</span><span class="p">;</span>

        <span class="sr">//</span> <span class="no">Point</span> <span class="n">at</span> <span class="n">pointer</span>
        <span class="no">Vector3</span> <span class="n">mousePosition</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Camera</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">main</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">ScreenToWorldPoint</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">Input</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">mousePosition</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="no">Vector2</span> <span class="n">direction</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">mousePosition</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">position</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">up</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">direction</span><span class="p">;</span>

        <span class="sr">//</span> <span class="no">Bullet</span> <span class="n">velocity</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">((</span><span class="no">Input</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">GetMouseButtonDown</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="n">bulletTimer</span> <span class="o">&lt;=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">))</span>
        <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="no">GameObject</span> <span class="n">newBullet</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Instantiate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bulletPrefab</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">transform</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">position</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">Quaternion</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">identity</span><span class="p">);</span>
            <span class="no">Rigidbody2D</span> <span class="n">bulletRigidbody</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">newBullet</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">GetComponent</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="no">Rigidbody2D</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">();</span>
            <span class="n">bulletRigidbody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">velocity</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">direction</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">normalized</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">bulletSpeed</span><span class="p">;</span>
            <span class="n">bulletTimer</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bulletTimer</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="n">bulletTimer</span> <span class="o">-=</span> <span class="no">Time</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">deltaTime</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="n">bulletBar</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">SetBulletBar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bulletTimer</span><span class="p">);</span>


    <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="n">void</span> <span class="no">OnTriggerEnter2D</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">Collider2D</span> <span class="n">other</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="sr">//</span> <span class="no">Check</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">other</span> <span class="no">GameObject</span> <span class="n">is</span> <span class="n">an</span> <span class="n">enemy</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">other</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">gameObject</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">CompareTag</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"Enemy"</span><span class="p">))</span>
        <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="n">health</span> <span class="o">-=</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">;</span>
            <span class="n">healthBar</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">SetHealthBar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">health</span><span class="p">);</span>
            <span class="no">Destroy</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">other</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">gameObject</span><span class="p">);</span>
            <span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">health</span> <span class="o">&lt;=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
            <span class="p">{</span>
                <span class="n">pauseScript</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">PauseGame</span><span class="p">();</span>
                <span class="no">GameObject</span> <span class="n">gameOver</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Instantiate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">gameOverPrefab</span><span class="p">);</span>
            <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>This exact code can be found on my github, or right <a href="https://github.com/Elijahtab/Cupids-Rocket">here</a>. Then I had to constrain my player within the boundaries of the screen.  This was the response given by ChatGPT when asked, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">How would I limit the player to the boundaries of the screen?</code></p>

<p><img src="/assets/bounds1.png" /></p>

<p>This snippet of code was one of the first, of many, mind-blowing moments as it worked perfectly as soon as I copy-pasted it into my script file. Go try this out yourself. You won’t get the same answer as me, but I guarantee it will be one that can be implemented in a Unity game.</p>

<p>While these were relatively widespread game mechanics that could be found in almost all starter Unity games, ChatGPT was able to help me with the not-so general stuff too. In order for my vision to work I needed a way for my enemy sprites to spawn, get across the screen. and then delete themselves. This was one of the harder parts. While I remembered making a despawner box from the previous quarter, I had forgotten the exact steps. So I asked ChatGPT.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/despawner1.png" /></p>

<p>Although this was all useful information which helped jog my caffeine-addled college brain, I needed a bit more. So I asked for specifics.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/despawnerr2.png" /></p>

<p>After getting the exact code and applying it to my quickly expanding game, I tested the despawner. Unfortunately it didn’t work, usually this would mean a long search involving google, stack exchange, discord and whatever else I could get my hands on. But why would I do that when GPT-3 was right there at my disposal? A simple question later, as well as some testing and my issues were solved.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/despawner3.png" /></p>

<p>This part truly bedazzled me. Because usually going through the ardous process of finding a stack exchange post that was related to my issue was in itself demoralising, and thats discounting actually fixing the problem itself. I was able to ask a simple question and get a simple response that was, almost, completely related to my query. And so, in no time my despawner was working perfectly well.</p>

<p>Now, I didn’t just use AI to help code my game, no, I went further than that. The main antagonist – of course coded with the help of ChatGPT – was a brand new image sourced from <a href="https://www.scenario.com/">Scenario.gg</a>. Scenario is a stable diffusion model that allows the user to create a generator, which is filled with similar images chosen by the user that are synthesized into a personal image creator which accepts prompts and images. I used a generator that was previously created by a user, the little robots generator.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/robotgen.png" height="226" width="219" /></p>

<p>The prompt I used was <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Little Robots, Evil robot, Flying, wings</code>, which generated this little guy.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/enemy.png" height="225" width="225" /></p>

<p>After playing around with transparency and alpha channels in gimp, my antagonist was born. But something was missing, the person this was all about. So I used the Anime Portraits generator, and inputted an image of my girlfriend as a reference for the Stable Diffusion model.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/jj.jpg" height="228" width="171" />  <img src="/assets/animegf.png" height="228" width="307" /></p>

<p>This image can be seen as the background for the main menu in the game. I was able to, with the help of AI, do the job of an artist myself. Artifical Intelligence, with my guidance and implementation, truly built this game. In fact, ChatGPT even helped me write this blog. The AIs answer to my asking for a critique of the blog post:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/blogcorrection2.png" /></p>

<p>After all of this prompting and implementing I was able to create a fully functional game that was even somewhat fun to play. And just in time for Valentines day.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/gamegif.gif" /></p>

<p>But, its not all rainbows and sunshine. ChatGPT has its fair share of issues. Asking it more complex questions often yields meager and chaotic results. And furthermore, the code it provides is not always foolproof, which can lead to some infuriating moments. For example while working on another game, ChatGPT provided me with defunct code that had been fazed out with a newer version of Unity. Or, when asked to create a script that allows for certain objects to be deactivated then reactivated, the AI failed to account for the fact that when a GameObject is deactivated in its entirety, you cannot refer to it by its tag. Thus, you have no way of reactivating it. And this is only talking about ChatGPT; the amount of times I was forced to regenerate images for Cupid’s Rocket because of lacking or disturbing outcomes was more than significant. This however, is an adolescent stage of Artificial Intelligence. And these issues will assuredly fade. As this technology develops, whatever I was shocked by during the creation of this game will surely become commonplace. Coding projects that were once the domain of well-payed professionals may become no more than a click away. And while this game is relatively basic, which may reflect both my novelty and the relative infancy of artificial intelligence, it is still, in my opinion a truly awe-inspiring glance into the future of game design and by extension of the world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="First" /><category term="Game" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s a quiet saturday and I’m studying for an upcoming test. As I survey the study lounge that is my home until the clock strikes eleven, I note the usual types – anxious procrastinators making up for lost time, socializers pretending to study, snackers that never seem to stop their chewing – but something feels off, a foreboding feeling saturates the room. My worries are actualized with a slight ping – a text from my girlfriend professing her excitement at the gift she’s gotten me for Valentines day. Horror engulfs me. How could I have forgotten, Valentine’s is only four days away and I have no gift at the ready.]]></summary></entry></feed>